I dedicated the past two years to understanding
لقد خصصت العامين الماضيين لكي أفهم
how people achieve their dreams.
كيف يحقق الناس أحلامهم.
When we think about the dreams we have,
عندما نفكر في أحلامنا،
and the dent we want to leave in the universe,
والأثر الذي نريد أن نتركه في هذا العالم،
it is striking to see how big of an overlap there is
فمن المدهش أن نرى التداخل الكبير
between the dreams that we have, and projects that never happen.
بين الأحلام التي لدينا والمشاريع التي لا تتحقق أبدا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I'm here to talk to you today
لذلك أنا هنا لأتحدث إليكم اليوم
about five ways how not to follow your dreams.
حول خمس طرق تساعدكم على عدم تحقيق أحلامكم.
One: Believe in overnight success.
أولاً : آمن بوجود نجاح يتحقق بين عشية وضحاها.
You know the story, right?
أنتم تفهمون قصدي ، أليس كذلك؟
The tech guy built a mobile app and sold it very fast for a lot of money.
كشخص مهتم بالتقنية صمم تطبيقاً للمحمول وباعه بسرعة مقابل الكثير من المال.
You know, the story may seem real, but I bet it's incomplete.
أتعلمون، قد تبدو هذه قصة حقيقية ولكن أراهن أنها قصة غير مكتملة.
If you go investigate further,
إذا تعمقت في البحث أكثر،
the guy has done 30 apps before
سنكتشف أن ذلك الرجل صمم 30 تطبيق من قبل
and he has done a master's on the topic, a PhD.
و لديه رسالة ماجستير بذلك التخصص، درجة الدكتوراه.
He has been working on the topic for 20 years.
و كان يعمل على هذا المشروع منذ 20 عاما.
This is really interesting.
هذا مثير للاهتمام حقا.
I myself have a story in Brazil that people think is an overnight success.
أنا نفسي لي قصة في البرازيل ظن الناس أنها نجاح بين عشية وضحاها.
I come from a humble family,
لقد نشأت من أسرة متواضعة
and two weeks before the deadline to apply for MIT,
وقبل انتهاء مهلة التقديم لمعهد ماساتشوستس للتقنية بأسبوعين،
I started the application process.
بدأت إعداد أوراق التقديم.
And, voilà! I got in.
و هكذا ! حصلت على القبول.
People may think it's an overnight success,
قد يظن الناس أن هذا نجاح بين عشية وضحاها،
but that only worked because for the 17 years prior to that,
ولكن هذا حدث لأنني لمدة 17 عاما قبل ذلك،
I took life and education seriously.
أخذت الحياة والتعليم على محمل الجد.
Your overnight success story is always a result
النجاح بين عشية وضحاها هو دائما نتيجة
of everything you've done in your life through that moment.
لكل شيء قمت به في حياتك حتى تلك اللحظة.
Two: Believe someone else has the answers for you.
ثانياً : آمن أن الآخرين يمتلكون أجوبة على أسئلتك.
Constantly, people want to help out, right?
على الدوام، يريد الناس أن يقدموا لك النصح، صحيح؟
All sorts of people: your family, your friends, your business partners,
كل الناس: عائلتك، وأصدقائك، وشركاء عملك،
they all have opinions on which path you should take:
جميعا لديهم آراء حول المسار الذي يجب أن تأخذه:
"And let me tell you, go through this pipe."
واسمح لي أن أقول لك، ادخل هذا النفق"
But whenever you go inside,
لكن حالما تدخل إلى الداخل،
there are other ways you have to pick as well.
ستجد أن هناك طرقا أخرى عليك أن تختارها أيضا.
And you need to make those decisions yourself.
وسيكون عليك أن تتخذ تلك القرارات بنفسك.
No one else has the perfect answers for your life.
فلا أحد غيرك لديه إجابة مثالية لحياتك.
And you need to keep picking those decisions, right?
و يتوجب عليك الاستمرار في اتخاذ تلك القرارات، أليس كذلك؟
The pipes are infinite and you're going to bump your head,
الأنابيب و الطرق لا متناهية و قد تضرب رأسك،
and it's a part of the process.
و هذا جزء من العملية.
Three, and it's very subtle but very important:
ثالثاً، وهي خفية على الكثير ولكنها نقطة مهمة:
Decide to settle when growth is guaranteed.
و هي الركون للسكينة حين يكون النمو شيئا مضمونا.
So when your life is going great,
لذلك عندما تسير حياتك بشكل رائع،
you have put together a great team,
بعد أن شكلت فريقا عظيما،
and you have growing revenue, and everything is set --
وكانت إيراداتك متنامية، و كل شيء مستقرا--
time to settle.
حان الوقت للسكون.
When I launched my first book,
عندما نشرت أول كتاب لي،
I worked really, really hard to distribute it everywhere in Brazil.
عملت بكل جهد، بجهد كبير حقاً لتوزيعه في كل مكان في البرازيل.
With that, over three million people downloaded it,
و قد تم تحميله من أكثر من ثلاثة ملايين شخص،
over 50,000 people bought physical copies.
و بعت منه أكثر من 50 ألف نسخة ورقية.
When I wrote a sequel, some impact was guaranteed.
عندما كتبت جزء آخر، كان بعض التأثير مضمونا.
Even if I did little, sales would be OK.
وحتى لو قمت بالقليل من الجهد فإن المبيعات ستكون على ما يرام.
But OK is never OK.
ولكن على ما يرام ليس على ما يرام أبدا.
When you're growing towards a peak,
حين تصعد نحو قمة ما،
you need to work harder than ever and find yourself another peak.
عليك أن تعمل بجهد أكثرلتجد لنفسك قمة أخرى.
Maybe if I did little,
ربما لو أنني بذلت جهدا صغيرا،
a couple hundred thousand people would read it,
كان ليقرأه بضعة آلاف من الناس،
and that's great already.
وهذا أمر عظيم أيضا.
But if I work harder than ever,
ولكن إذا عملت بجهد أكثر من أي وقت مضى،
I can bring this number up to millions.
فيمكنني أن أوصل هذا الرقم إلى الملايين.
That's why I decided, with my new book, to go to every single state of Brazil.
لهذا السبب قررت حين أصدرت كتابي الجديد زيارة كل ولاية من ولايات البرازيل.
And I can already see a higher peak.
و يمكنني أن أرى قمة أعلى منذ الآن.
There's no time to settle down.
ليس هناك وقت للاستقرار.
Fourth tip, and that's really important:
رابعاً، و هي نقطة مهمة حقاً:
Believe the fault is someone else's.
أن تلقي اللوم على شخص آخر غير نفسك.
I constantly see people saying,
أرى الناس يقولون باستمرار،
"Yes, I had this great idea, but no investor had the vision to invest."
كانت لدي فكرة عظيمة لكن لم يكن مستثمر يمتلك الرؤية للاستثمار فيها."
"Oh, I created this great product,
أوه، لقد اخترعت هذا المنتج العظيم،
but the market is so bad, the sales didn't go well."
لكن السوق سيء للغاية، فلم تسر المبيعات على ما يرام."
Or, "I can't find good talent; my team is so below expectations."
أو، "لا أستطيع أن أجد المواهب الجيدة؛ فريقي مستواه دون التوقعات."
If you have dreams,
إن كانت لديك أحلام،
it's your responsibility to make them happen.
فهي مسؤوليتك أن تجعلها تتحقق.
Yes, it may be hard to find talent.
نعم، قد يكون من الصعب العثور على المواهب.
Yes, the market may be bad.
نعم، قد يكون السوق سيئا.
But if no one invested in your idea,
ولكن إن لم يستثمر أحد في فكرتك،
if no one bought your product,
إن لم يشتر أحد منتجك،
for sure, there is something there that is your fault.
بالتأكيد، هناك خطب ما تتحمل مسؤوليته.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Definitely.
لا شك في ذلك.
You need to get your dreams and make them happen.
عليك أن تأخذ أحلامك أحلامك و تحققها.
And no one achieved their goals alone.
ومامن أحد حقق أحلامه بمفرده.
But if you didn't make them happen, it's your fault and no one else's.
و إن لم تحقق أحلامك، فهذا خطؤك أنت، وليس خطأ أحد غيرك.
Be responsible for your dreams.
كن مسؤولا عن أحلامك.
And one last tip, and this one is really important as well:
وهناك نصيحة أخرى و هي مهمة حقاً:
Believe that the only things that matter are the dreams themselves.
و هي : آمن أن الشيء الوحيد الذي يهم هي الأحلام ذاتها.
Once I saw an ad, and it was a lot of friends,
رأيت أحد الإعلانات ذات مرة في الإعلان كان هناك الكثير من الأصدقاء،
they were going up a mountain, it was a very high mountain,
كانوا في طريقهم إلى أعلى الجبل وكان الجبل عاليا جدا،
and it was a lot of work.
و يتطلب تسلقه الكثير من الجهد.
You could see that they were sweating and this was tough.
يمكنك أن ترى المتسلقين يتصببون عرقا، وأن ذلك كان صعبا.
And they were going up, and they finally made it to the peak.
و استمروا في طريقهم نحو القمة حتى وصلوا.
Of course, they decided to celebrate, right?
وبطبيعة الحال، قرروا الاحتفال، أليس كذلك؟
I'm going to celebrate, so, "Yes! We made it, we're at the top!"
و عليه سوف أحتفل "نعم! لقد وصلنا إلى القمة، لقد نجحنا!"
Two seconds later, one looks at the other and says,
بعد ثانيتين ، نظر أحدهم إلى الآخر وقال :
"OK, let's go down."
حسنا، هيا نعد أدراجنا و ننزل."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Life is never about the goals themselves.
لا تتعلق الحياة مطلقاً بالأهداف ذاتها.
Life is about the journey.
الحياة هي الرحلة نحو الهدف.
Yes, you should enjoy the goals themselves,
نعم، يجب أن تتمتع بالأهداف،
but people think that you have dreams,
لكن الناس يعتقدون أن لديك أحلاما ما،
and whenever you get to reaching one of those dreams,
و حالما تحقق واحدا من تلك الأحلام،
it's a magical place where happiness will be all around.
سوف تصل إلى مكان سحري حيث السعادة في كل مكان.
But achieving a dream is a momentary sensation,
ولكن تحقيق الحلم هو إحساس لحظي،
and your life is not.
لكن حياتك ليست كذلك.
The only way to really achieve all of your dreams
والطريقة الوحيدة لتحقيق كل أحلامك حقا
is to fully enjoy every step of your journey.
هو التمتع المطلق بكل خطوة من خطوات رحلتك.
That's the best way.
هذه هي الطريقة المثلى.
And your journey is simple -- it's made of steps.
رحلتك بسيطة-- فهي مجموع خطواتك.
Some steps will be right on.
بعض الخطوات ستكون صحيحة.
Sometimes you will trip.
وفي بعض الأحيان ستتعثر.
If it's right on, celebrate, because some people wait a lot to celebrate.
إن كانت صحيحة، فاحتفل، لأن بعض الناس ينتظرون كثيرا للاحتفال.
And if you tripped, turn that into something to learn.
و إن كانت خطوتك عثرة، فحاول أن تتعلم منها.
If every step becomes something to learn or something to celebrate,
فإن أصبحت كل خطوة شيئا تتعلم منه أو تحتفل به،
you will for sure enjoy the journey.
فإنك بالتأكيد ستستمتع بالرحلة.
So, five tips:
إذاً خمس نصائح :
Believe in overnight success,
آمن أن النجاح ممكن بين عشية وضحاها،
believe someone else has the answers for you,
آمن أن الآخرين يمتلكون الأجوبة بدلا عنك،
believe that when growth is guaranteed, you should settle down,
آمن أنه ما إن ضمنت النمو فإنه يجب أن تستكين،
believe the fault is someone else's,
آمن الخطأ ليس خطأك،
and believe that only the goals themselves matter.
آمن أن الأهداف لذاتها هي المهمة فقط.
Believe me, you do that, and you will destroy your dreams.
صدقوني، إذا فعلتم ذلك، سوف تدمرون أحلامكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكراً لكم